Contact

metaimagem@gmail.com

www.linkedin.com/in/ rogeriolourenco (LinkedIn) www.labedis.mn.ufrj.br/index.php (Company) lattes.cnpq.br/4893226453148605 (Portfolio)

Top Skills

A/B Testing

User Experience Testing

User Interviews

Languages

Français (Limited Working)

English (Full Professional)

Portugais (Native or Bilingual)

Espagnol (Professional Working)

Certifications

Adobe ActionScript

Ethnographic Research Design and Innovation

Honors-Awards

Prix Ars Electronica Honorary Mention 2010 - Digital Communities

Publications

Discurso e Imagem nos Enunciados Matemáticos

Video-Identity:Images and Sounds of Citizenship Construction in Brazil

A contagem discursiva: uma análise dos enunciados de provas de matemática

Tropixel: etnomatemática como tecnologia simbólica

Rogerio Lourenco

Information Ethnographer

Rio de Janeiro, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

Summary

I am a qualitative researcher with over ten years of professional expertise; working with

firms, governments and industries. Since 2019, I have been building, researching, and designing science-

based user experience solutions for market needs. I have collaborated with distributed teams

in Brazil, United States, Mexico, Finland, Thailand, Belgium, France, Sweden, and India.

======>

A bit more of context:

I am a highly skilled researcher with expertise in anthropology, linguistics, and information architecture. I use science-based methods to deliver impactful results that minimize risks and drive business outcomes. With over 10 years of experience, I have collaborated with teams using agile methodologies across the globe. My interest is crafting factual user experience analysis for diverse industries, government policies, and EdTech, and Knowledge and Language Ops initiatives.

On dialogic environments, I strive to bring the best possible product insights to market by leveraging my expertise in research, production, documentation, and data analysis.

Experience

Laboratório de Estudos do Discurso, Imagem e Som Research Associate 2014 - Present (10 years)

Extensive experience in interdisciplinary research in Discourse Analysis across various contexts (editor, curator, researcher, etc.), Urban Culture, Media Theory, and Educational Technology

Focus on linguistic research in mathematics education and the development of app prototypes

Experience applying social sciences to digital products such as courses and as an Al consultant (Sina app)

Experience in user research methodologies (e.g., ethnography, usability testing, surveys)

Experience in documentation management, including taxonomies, controlled vocabularies, and system implementation

Familiarity with bureaucratic and administrative processes

Skills in analysis, synthesis, problem-solving, strategy, communication, and presentation

Design and maintenance of the laboratory website from concept (HTML page and logo)

arara school

Professor

November 2021 - Present (3 years)

Sao Paulo, São Paulo, Brésil

Linguistics and anthropology can be very helpful in usability tests. They can be scientific methods for collecting and analyzing qualitative data and observing human behavior.

In this course, I adapted these principles to provide methods and insights into user experience, enabling the improvement of digital products and services.

The Usability module includes topics such as:

Initial presentation and specialist presentation;

Concept and context of usability;

Difference between method, test, and analysis;

Types of tests;

Planning, production, and conducting of tests;

Test recording techniques;

Test analysis techniques;

Presentation and diverse audiences;

Documentation for research.

https://www.arara.school/cursos/online/design-conversacional

Cross Project Resources

UX Researcher June 2022 - August 2022 (3 months)

Sinch

UX Researcher

November 2021 - June 2022 (8 months)

Rio de Janeiro, Brésil

As part of my B2B activities, I have conducted various research and discovery initiatives, including:

Co-Creation Discovery Sessions:

Facilitated sessions where sales team members trialed demo products and provided feedback.

Results: Product features were refined and improved based on feedback.

Interviews with Internal Clients:

Designed, conducted, and analyzed interviews with internal clients across several projects.

Results: Gained insights into client needs and preferences. New products were developed and enhanced.

Personas Development:

Developed personas for products through collaborative processes.

Results: Products were tailored to target audience needs and preferences.

Software Documentation:

Analyzed and produced documentation for internal products.

Results: Documentation was clear, comprehensive, and user-friendly.

Conversational Analysis:

Conducted an analysis of over 800 conversational flows during discovery processes.

Results: Understood internal team-client communication dynamics. Enhanced product integration with

API needs and ecosystem scalability.

Throughout these initiatives, I collaborated with teams in various regions with different levels of UX maturity.

Results: Integrated messaging products with 80% of the largest communication app ecosystems.

IVOW AI, Inc. Artificial Intelligence Consultant July 2020 - August 2020 (2 months) Washington, États-Unis

Problem: They had a code challenge that offered financial prizes for solutions. They got vague information made on a biased corpus from Wikipedia. This highlighted the need for someone with expertise in culture and producing non-biased data.

Solution: As a research consultant, I suggested an "algorithmic path" to be implemented by the machine learning team instead of relying solely on a constructed linguistic corpus.

This project was recognized by Project Voice's Google Assistant Developer and Voice Medal for Diversity and Inclusion of 2021.

Mutant UX VUI Designer October 2019 - April 2020 (7 months) Région de São Paulo, Brésil

UX design for voice interfaces in conversational IVR (URA and VDA).

Worked in agile environment, having lean as guide for:

- Designed the client's pre-paid mobile flows (IVR) customer support.
- Redesigned the service flow with VDA's for TV and Internet customer support.

Developed, Designed and tested conversations with:

User journey for voice / text interfaces
Sample Dialog, Voice Direction
Usability tests, surveys
Persona creation
Discourse analysis, Interviews, elicitation
Documentation (low and high fidelity)

RNP

Digital Memory Curator November 2009 - September 2010 (11 months)

Role:

Consultant for a collaborative project between the Brazilian Ministry of Culture and the National Education and Research Network (RNP), involving Instituto do Patrimônio Histórico de Artístico Nacional (Iphan), Agência Nacional do Cinema (Ancine), Fundação Nacional de Artes (Funarte), Instituto Brasileiro de Museus (Ibram), and Fundação Biblioteca Nacional (FBN).

Problem:

Many public museums and cultural institutions lacked the technology to effectively serve remote regions and democratize access to information and culture.

Solution:

Conducted ethnographic research to understand how national public service staff used technology. Based on these insights, recommendations were made, and visualizations were created to integrate information, maps, and cultural needs for policymakers. This systematization supported the formulation of public policies aimed at improving digital accessibility in cultural institutions.

Responsibilities:

Conducted ethnographic research on technology use by public service staff.

Conducted language and culture assessments for improvement areas.

Made recommendations and created visualizations for policymakers.

Systematized online forum discussions to formulate public policies.

Leveraged digital solutions to enhance cultural access in remote regions.

Tasks by (DoD):

Developed reports to improve public policies on digital archives.

Facilitated online forums, workshops, and seminars on digital archives.

Conducted focus groups and interviews on cultural practices and attitudes.

Analyzed data and made recommendations for improving cultural competency.

MultiRio - Municipal Multimidia Company 7 years 9 months

Research and Documentation Manager January 2005 - December 2008 (4 years)

Rio de Janeiro Area, Brazil

Responsibilities:

Coordinated research and documentation planning for MULTIRIO products for television, internet, and press

Led the conception, development, and setup of the company's digital archiving system, integrating analog and digital media with controlled vocabularies.

Supervised and coordinated the implementation of the company's thesaurus Coordinated staff for the 4th World Media Summit for Children and Adolescents

Managed a team of 12 people

Led cross-functional teams to achieve project goals

Conducted research and development to improve content production and distribution

Utilized controlled vocabularies to ensure consistency and accuracy in content Developed and implemented digital strategies to enhance product offerings and user engagement

Managed projects from conception to completion, ensuring timely delivery and quality control

Documented all aspects of projects for future reference and continuous improvement

Key Skills:

Expertise in social sciences
Cross-functional team leadership
Research and development (R&D)
Controlled vocabularies
Digital strategy
Project management

Documentation

Results:

Improved coordination and planning of research and documentation in all company media types

Successfully implemented the company's thesaurus and digital archiving system

Effectively coordinated the staff for the 4th World Media Summit for Children and Adolescents

Managed a team of 12 people, achieving project goals

Enhanced content production and distribution through research and development

Ensured content consistency and accuracy using controlled vocabularies Increased product offerings and user engagement through digital strategies Delivered projects on time with quality control

Maintained comprehensive documentation for future reference and continuous improvement

Documented all aspects of projects for future reference and continuous improvement.

Content Researcher

April 2001 - December 2004 (3 years 9 months)

Rio de Janeiro Area, Brazil

Conducted media research and production across TV, Press, and the Internet

Participated in fieldwork, facilitation, documentation, content production, and strategy development for various projects

Designed and executed research studies on digital educational tools for primary and secondary education

Analyzed research data and presented findings to stakeholders

Collaborated with cross-functional teams to develop and improve digital educational products and services

Contributed to the development of innovative educational tools, resulting in increased adoption rates among educators and improved learning outcomes for students

Coordinated staff for the 4th World Summit for Children and Youth, in 2004, leveraging expertise in facilitating young people and media research.

Turner Broadcasting Fulbright-Turner Program September 1999 - March 2000 (7 months)

Greater Atlanta Area

Image researcher for "Sala de Notícias", the Canal Futura's news journal. Project reporting and elaboration between Brazilian schools and the CNN newsroom staff at Turner Learning.

The World Bank

Internship at the Latin American and the Caribbean Communications Office

October 1999 - December 1999 (3 months)

Designed and updated the content of the websites for Latin America and the Caribbean region, as well as provided assistance in video production.

As an intern in strategic communication, I horned HTML, documentation, and research allowing me to successfully create engaging and effective content.

I worked independently on all these tasks, ensuring high-quality results. You can view an archived version of the website at:

https://web.archive.org/web/20000511174712/http://wbln0018.worldbank.org/external/lac/lac.nsf.

Education

UFRJ - Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro Ph.D, Linguistics · (2011 - 2015)

UFRJ - Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro Pós Graduação em Gramática Gerativa e Estudos de Cognição - Museu Nacional, Linguistics · (2010 - 2011)

Universidade Federal Fluminense MS, Communications · (1997 - 2000)

Georgia State University
Visitant Scholar, Communications · (1999 - 1999)

UFRJ - Universidade Federal do Rio de Janeiro BA, Anthropology · (1993 - 1997)